Alhassan Osman

+44 (0)7851608971 richosmanthus@gmail.com 161, Selkirk Drive – Oakridge Park MK14 6FH – Milton Keynes

PERSONAL STATEMENT

An experience web applications developer and advanced knowledge in the software development paradigm with over five years working experience as a IT software applications developer and manager. Quick to learn and adapt to new technology, equally successful in both team and self – directed environments of work. Proficient skills in a wide range of computer systems, programming languages, tools and testing methodologies. Academic and project experience has enabled the development of outstanding communication skills with fluency in English and other local Ghanaian dialects and an effective relationship builder with both clients and internal stakeholders. Also well organized, dedicated and goal oriented individual with leadership capabilities. In-depth experience of computers in business and associated application such as: Microsoft word, excel, PowerPoint, outlook, MS project, etc.

KEY ACHIEVEMENTS

- Recognised for consistently meeting and exceeding performance expectations and promoted to Assistant Manager of the IT Division and heading the applications development and helpdesk unit.
- Recognised for been the most efficient and hardworking IT support staff for two years consecutively.
- Recognised for successfully implementing the National SIM Card Registration Exercise in Ghana as a project coordinator for the Authority
- Awarded scholarship to the Cranfield University for an MSc. in Computational and Software Techniques in Engineering in 2016/17.

EDUCATION

MSc Computational & Software Techniques in Engineering: Cranfield University, Cranfield, UK (September 2016 - September 2017) (Yet to be Completed)

- Modules: C++, Computational Methods, Computer Graphics, Management for Technology, Requirement
 Analysis & System Design, Software Testing & Quality Assurance, High Performance Technical
 Computing, Cloud Computing, Advanced Java and Small Scale Parallel Programming.
- **Group Design Project**: Applications in High End Computing: The aim of the assignment is to apply collective knowledge, from the modules you have attended during your MSc studies in Software Engineering for Technical Computing, on the area of fluid dynamics simulation and visualization
- Individual Thesis (Yet to be Completed): A Web-Based Application for Visualizing 3D Data Arising from Solution of a PDE.

MA Economic Policy Management: University of Ghana, Legon, Ghana (August 2013 – July 2014)

- Modules: Programme & Project Management, Development Economics, Financial Management, Strategic Management, Econometrics, Rural Economy, Microeconomics for Policy Analysis, Macroeconomics for Policy Analysis, Effective Communications, Research Methods, Public Sector Economics, Economics Policy Seminar, Mathematical & Statistical Methods for Policy and Managerial Accounting.
- **Individual Thesis:** The transition from analogue to digital broadcasting, an examination of the various options of incentivizing the consumer and its impact on the Ghanaian economy

B.ED Computer Science: University of Cape Coast, Ghana (August 2006 - May 2010)

Modules:

• **Individual Project Work**: An Online system that allows senior members and senior staffs of the university to apply for new appointments and promotions through the Internet instead of the usual manual system.

CAREER HISTORY

National Communications Authority (NCA): Accra – Assistant Manager, IT (January 2016 – September 2017)

- As the head of IT applications and helpdesk Unit head, ensured timely response to helpdesk issues in terms of network and systems Administration support for staff.
- Developed an In-House helpdesk application for staff to generate tickets of incidence for immediate support from the team. It also allows the team to keep a log of incidence resolution procedure which serves as a first quide to the staff before IT helpdesk assistant arrives.
- Performed several training for stuff on how to perform basic network and systems troubleshooting such as;
 Internet downtime, printer connectivity issues, email issues, antivirus issues, MS productivity tools, etc.
- Responsible for handling of the Authority's Active Directory administration by setting rules and policies for
 users on the domain, creating users and putting them in different groups with different accesses to
 resources on the domain and network.
- Possess skills in the administration and troubleshooting of the Authority's mail system which is hosted inhouse on Zimbra mail server which Linux based.
- Successfully developed a Complaint Management system (http://complaints.nca.org.gh) for the Authority to enable complainants lodge complaints online.
- Managed the Implementation of the Government's E-Learning Management System for the Authority and trained staff members on the usage of the system.
- Managed the successful development of the Authority's new website design (http://nca.org.gh).

National Communications Authority (NCA): Accra - Officer, IT (March 2012 - December 2015)

Established in 1996, the Authority is a Government regulator under the Communications ministry responsible for regulating the communications industry and its infrastructure in the country.

- Supervision of the Authority's IT helpdesk team to effectively deliver prompt IT support to all staff.
- Responsible for ensuring that the Authority's backup routine is carried out as scheduled in a timely and effective manner. This included onsite on DR site backups with Acronis.
- Coordination of the SIM Registration exercise in Ghana by supervising over 20 contract staff to ensure the smooth verification of mobile phone subscribers to enable the project meet its objectives
- Assisted in the development and maintenance of the Real Time Verification System which is used to verify subscribers in real-time upon SIM Registration.
- Management of the Authority's current website (http://nca.org.gh) by regularly updating and improving certain features and content of the site.
- Currently leading a development team to redesign the Authority's website to enhance its look and feel and also bring up to scale with current web technologies.
- Developed a Type Approval and Dealership License portal (http://portal.nca.org.gh) for the Authority to enable its customers apply for these services online.
- Management of the software applications which are database driven by providing first hand support to the
 applications (ASMS system for Spectrum analysis and monitoring, ASCOM QoS system for the monitoring
 and measurements of the quality of service of the various mobile network operators, and the PERSOL &
 PASTEL systems for the Accountants) to enable the Authority deliver on its core mandate

National Communications Authority (NCA): Accra – National Service, IT (October 2010 – July 2011)

- Provided IT helpdesk support to the staff of the Authority.
- Member of a committee to carry out a revenue collection exercise for the Authority.
- Member of the SIM Registration exercise team to carry out monitoring of the registration exercise on the field across the length and breadth of Ghana.
- Assisted in the updating of the Authority's website content.

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

- International Certification: PHP Zend Certified Engineer Koenig Institute, India, August 2014
- Certificate: Advanced Certificate in Network Administration (CCNA)
 Ghana Institute of Management and Public Administration (GIMPA), November 2013
 Accra, Ghana
- Certificate: Introduction to ICT Policy and Regulation
 Commonwealth Telecommunications Organization, July 2013
 Akosombo, Ghana
- Certificate: Competition and Convergence
 Commonwealth Telecommunications Organization, July 2013
 Akosombo, Ghana
- Certificate: Scalable Internet Services (SSE)
 African Network Operators Group (AfNOG), June 2013
 Lusaka, Zambia
- Certificate of Appreciation: West African Cybersecurity and Cybercrime workshop US Department of State and the US Department of Justice, January 2013 Accra, Ghana
- Certificate: Advanced Certificate in Database Administration
 Ghana Institute of Management and Public Administration (GIMPA), October 2012
 Accra, Ghana
- Certificate: Wireless Network Security Workshop
 Ghana Telecom University College (GTUC), September 2011,
 Accra, Ghana

CONFERENCES AND WORKSHOPS

- Annual Cyber Security Forum, April 2013
 Yaounde, Cameroon
- ITU-T Study Group 11: Signaling and Test Protocols Specifications
 International Telecommunications Union Headquarters, March 2013
 Geneva, Switzerland
- Microsoft OPEN DOOR Conference
 Accra International Conference Centre, April 2011
 Accra, Ghana

SKILLS, INTERESTS & EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

Languages: Fluent English, Twi, Fante, Hausa, Dagomba and Ga.

IT Skills:

IDE: Eclipse, Visual Studio, Dreamweaver

Hosting:
 Virtual Hosting (using apache on Ubuntu Linux Server), CPanel

Data Recovery tools: Tune-up Utilities, Power Data Recovery, Acronis

Methodologies: Waterfall, RAD.

XML: XML Schema, DTD, XPath

Programming C++, C, PHP, SQL, HTML, JavaScript, CSS, basic knowledge in Qt, Java,

Languages: OpenMP.

Servers: Windows Server 2003, 2008 and Ubuntu Linux Server

Windows XP, Windows Vista, Windows 7, Server 2003, Linux (Ubuntu **Operating Systems**

Desktop, Ubuntu Server)

Virtualization Platform: Oracle Virtual Box

RDBMS/Tools: MySQL, Microsoft Access

Networking: Subnetting, Routing, Cabling, Trunking

Content Management: Wordpress

Individual Interests: Reading, listening to music, scrabble, swimming and teaching.